Did you lie to me?
나한테 거짓말했어요?
I didn't lie.
나는 거짓말을 하지 않았습니다.
So what was it?
그래서 그것은 무엇이었나요?
It's just...
그것은 단지 ...
I was trying to find the right moment.
나는 적절한 순간을 찾으려고 노력했습니다.
Were you ever going to tell me
나한테 말하려고 한 적 있었어?
or were you going to keep lying?
아니면 계속 거짓말을 할 건가요?
If I tried to hide it, I wouldn't have told you.
숨기려고 했다면 말하지 않았을 거예요.
So it wasn't the right time?
그럼 때가 아니었나요?
I did not mean that.
그런 뜻은 아니었어요.
So what do you mean?
그럼 무슨 말이에요?
You say you don't have a son?
아들이 없다고 하던가요?
Did it seem that easy to you?
그게 그렇게 쉬워 보였나요?
Did you think I was so alone
내가 너무 혼자라고 생각했나요?
I wouldn't mind if you had a child?
아이가 있어도 상관없겠죠?
Anything else you want to confess?
또 고백하고 싶은 게 있나요?
Any criminal record?
범죄기록은 없나요?
I was afraid you would react like that...
그런 반응을 보일까봐 두려웠어요...
That's why it was difficult for me to tell you.
그래서 당신에게 말하기가 어려웠습니다.
I was afraid...
두려웠어요...
because I like you a lot.
왜냐하면 나는 당신을 많이 좋아하기 때문입니다.
How do you think that makes me feel?
그것이 내 기분을 어떻게 만든다고 생각하나요?
I hate myself for loving you,
당신을 사랑한 내가 미워요
for trusting someone like you.
당신 같은 사람을 신뢰했기 때문에.
I regret it a lot.
많이 후회해요.
[Do Hyun]
[도현]
I'll stop by this weekend to get my things.
이번 주말에 물건을 가지러 들르겠습니다.
If it makes you uncomfortable, I will come when you are not at home.
불편하시다면 집에 없을 때 찾아오겠습니다.
[Idiot]
[바보]
- Hello. - Where are you?
- 안녕하세요. - 어디 계시나요?
- At home. - What are you doing?
- 집에서. - 뭐하고 있어요?
I have an existential crisis.
나는 실존 위기에 처해 있습니다.
Some create masterpieces at 18,
누군가는 18세에 걸작을 만들고,
and others
그리고 다른 사람들
they are 27 and correct typographical errors of others.
그들은 27살이에요 다른 사람의 인쇄상의 오류를 수정합니다.
I'm going there.
나는 거기로 갈 것이다.
I just showered and changed.
방금 샤워하고 옷을 갈아입었어요.
So what? Just wait for me.
그래서 뭐? 나를 기다려주세요.
- Know? - That?
- 알다? - 저것?
You don't usually try that hard in life.
당신은 인생에서 보통 그렇게 열심히 노력하지 않습니다.
Don't start, just read it.
시작하지 말고 그냥 읽어 보세요.
Do graduate students Do they always write such long essays?
대학원생도 해라 그들은 항상 그렇게 긴 에세이를 쓰나요?
Is it too much?
너무 많은가요?
There is a saying:
다음과 같은 말이 있습니다.
"I didn't have time to write a short letter,
"짧은 편지를 쓸 시간이 없었어요.
so I wrote a long one."
그래서 길게 썼어요."
It's by Mark Twain.
마크 트웨인의 작품입니다.
See?
보다?
The longer it is,
길어질수록,
more it shows that you are not ready.
더 나아가 그것은 당신이 준비되지 않았음을 보여줍니다.
So help me adjust it,
그러니 조정하는 데 도움을 주세요.
to make it precise and irrefutable.
정확하고 반박할 수 없게 만드는 것입니다.
let me benefit of the future great writer.
나에게 혜택을 줘 미래의 위대한 작가.
Good.
좋은.
That smells amazing.
냄새가 정말 대단해요.
It's crazy.
미친 짓이야.
It's delicious, right?
맛있지, 그렇지?
My parents returned to the field for their garden,
부모님은 정원을 가꾸기 위해 밭으로 돌아가셨고,
so I basically lived in your house and I ate all your food.
그래서 난 기본적으로 네 집에서 살았어 그리고 나는 당신의 음식을 모두 먹었습니다.
Yes, I told you to move.
응, 움직이라고 했잖아.
Clear.
분명한.
Your mom's kimchi fried rice was the best.
엄마가 해주신 김치볶음밥 최고였습니다.
Hey,
안녕,
what's wrong with you?
무슨 일이야?
I just miss your mom.
나는 단지 당신의 엄마가 그리워요.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Still, it feels good,
그래도 기분은 좋다,
because I can talk about my mother.
엄마에 대해 이야기할 수 있으니까요.
If I had known that he would leave so suddenly,
그 사람이 이렇게 갑자기 떠날 줄 알았더라면,
I would have tried harder
더 노력했을 텐데
to become someone sooner.
더 빨리 누군가가 되기 위해.
It's a real shame.
정말 부끄러운 일입니다.
[Listen 25 Minimarket]
[리슨25 미니마켓]
It seems the power went out.
전원이 나간 것 같습니다.
Do you have cash?
현금이 있나요?
No.
아니요.
I don't have cash either.
나도 현금이 없어.
I'll return this and leave.
이거 반납하고 떠날게요.
No, I'll take care of it.
아니요, 제가 처리하겠습니다.
Why is there no light?
왜 빛이 없나요?
Why is it so dark here?
여기는 왜 이렇게 어두워?
Give me a pack of cigarettes.
담배 한 갑 주세요.
Sorry, the power went out.
죄송합니다. 전원이 나갔습니다.
Do you have cash?
현금이 있나요?
Who carries cash nowadays?
요즘 누가 현금을 갖고 다니나요?
The box doesn't work, so the cards are useless.
상자가 작동하지 않습니다. 그래서 카드는 쓸모가 없습니다.
Now you disrespect me?
지금 당신은 나를 무례하게 생각합니까?
Do you look down on me?
당신은 나를 무시합니까?
What are you taking about?
당신은 무엇을 복용하고 있습니까?
He said the cards don't work because of the blackout.
카드가 안 된다고 하더군요 정전 때문에.
Who the hell are you?
도대체 당신은 누구입니까?
-And who the hell are you? - That?
- 대체 당신은 누구죠? - 저것?
How dare they?
어떻게 감히?
You two...
너희 둘은...
Give me the cigarettes now!
당장 담배 주세요!
Yes sir.
네, 선생님.
What are you looking at?
무엇을 보고 있나요?
Police? I'm in a store in the Yeonhwa neighborhood.
경찰? 나는 가게에 있어요 연화동네에서.
There's a drunk here.
여기 술 취한 사람이 있어요.
He throws things and threatens us.
그는 물건을 던지고 우리를 위협합니다.
Please come immediately.
즉시 오십시오.
It seems that the entire area is in darkness.
일대 전체가 어둠 속에 있는 것 같습니다.
My boss told us to close until the light came back.
우리 상사가 문 닫으라고 했어 빛이 돌아올 때까지.
I can't serve customers,
고객에게 서비스를 제공할 수 없습니다.
just in case that things get out of control.
혹시라도 상황이 통제 불능이 되는 거죠.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
You can close the door.
문을 닫으시면 됩니다.
Do you want me to stay with you?
내가 당신과 함께 있기를 원하시나요?
If I go home, it will be dark too,
집에가면 날도 어두워지겠지
and I don't even have candles.
그리고 촛불도 없어요.
Those who listen to "Night Walk" They have known it for a while:
'Night Walk'를 듣는 분들 그들은 한동안 그것을 알고 있었습니다:
I love cherry blossoms.
저는 벚꽃을 좋아합니다.
You hear this, right?
이 말 들리죠?
Spring It came especially late this year.
봄 올해는 특히 늦게 찾아왔습니다.
I heard that the flowers would open late too,
꽃도 늦게 핀다고 들었는데,
so I waited and waited
그래서 기다리고 또 기다렸어요
in the hope of seeing them in full bloom,
꽃이 활짝 피어나기를 바라며
but a sudden rain He made them fall before their time.
근데 갑자기 비가 왔어 그는 그들을 제때에 넘어지게 만들었습니다.
In the end, I missed them.
결국 보고 싶었어요.
Why do good things Do they disappear so quickly?
좋은 일을 하는 이유 그렇게 빨리 사라지나요?
How did he hide that he had a son?
그는 아들이 있다는 사실을 어떻게 숨겼습니까?
One becomes two, and suddenly there are variables.
하나가 둘이 되고, 갑자기 변수가 생겼습니다.
No, actually there are three.
아니요, 실제로는 세 개가 있습니다.
Do you find it funny?
재미있나요?
At least he's not married.
적어도 그는 결혼하지 않았습니다.
And if he stays alone at Jun Kyung's house,
그리고 준경 집에 혼자 남게 된다면,
You are not raising your child.
당신은 아이를 키우는 것이 아닙니다.
What is the problem?
문제는 무엇입니까?
He's divorced, right?
그 사람 이혼했어요, 그렇죠?
- How old is the child? - Enough.
- 아이는 몇 살인가요? - 충분한.
What does that matter now?
지금 그게 무슨 상관이야?
Anyway, delete his number.
어쨌든 그 사람 전화번호는 삭제하세요.
If you save it, you will wait for me to call you
저장해두면 내가 전화할 때까지 기다리게 돼
and you will end up calling him when you feel alone.
외로움을 느낄 때 결국 그에게 전화하게 될 것입니다.
I already deleted it.
이미 삭제했습니다.
You probably memorized it.
당신은 아마 그것을 외웠을 것입니다.
Erase it from your head too.
머리에서도 지워보세요.
You need a drink.
음료수가 필요합니다.
Drink and forget everything.
마시고 모든 것을 잊어 버리십시오.
Let's drink.
마시자.
Are you really going to break up with him?
너 정말 그 사람이랑 헤어질 거야?
In fact, we're done.
사실, 우리는 끝났습니다.
Didn't you hear he has a son?
그에게 아들이 있다는 소식을 못 들었나요?
What better reason to break up?
헤어지는 데 더 좋은 이유는 무엇입니까?
Let's go...
가자...
It's like you always wait a reason to leave.
항상 기다리는 것처럼 떠나야 할 이유.
Did you hear his version?
그의 버전을 들어보셨나요?
The reason I didn't tell you?
내가 말하지 않은 이유는 무엇입니까?
Hey, you still love him, right?
이봐, 아직도 그 사람 사랑하지?
Isn't that a very strong reason to continue?
그것이 계속해야 할 매우 강력한 이유가 아닌가?
- Who is it? - Hey,
- 누구죠? - 안녕,
don't answer
대답하지 마세요
It's not Do Hyun.
도현이 아니에요.
You don't need to remember the number of a scammer.
기억할 필요는 없어 사기꾼의 수.
Hello?
안녕하세요?
Yeah.
응.
At first,
처음에는
this space asked for it a terminally ill father.
이 공간이 그걸 요구했어 불치병을 앓고 있는 아버지.
His family paid a deposit for months
그의 가족은 몇 달 동안 보증금을 지불했습니다
to reserve it specifically.
특별히 예약해 두세요.
There was an error on the part of our staff.
저희 직원의 실수가 있었습니다.
We sincerely apologize.
진심으로 사과드립니다.
How could something like this happen?
어떻게 이런 일이 일어날 수 있습니까?
I don't understand.
모르겠어요.
We were surprised too when we found out.
우리도 놀랐다 우리가 알았을 때.
Were you surprised?
놀랐나요?
Do you think this is like canceling a reservation at a restaurant?
이게 취소와 같다고 생각하시나요? 레스토랑 예약이요?
We have nothing more to say.
우리는 더 이상 할 말이 없습니다.
That's all?
그게 다야?
Once again, We offer you our most sincere apologies.
다시 한번, 진심으로 사과드립니다.
Do you think an apology will fix this?
사과하면 해결될 것 같나요?
So is there any space left?
그럼 남은 공간이 있나요?
Yes. Please follow me.
예. 저를 따라오세요.
Here.
여기.
Thank you all for this great day.
이 좋은 하루를 보내주신 모든 분들께 감사드립니다.
Yes, thanks!
네, 감사합니다!
We will return to our hotels and rest,
우리는 호텔로 돌아가 휴식을 취할 예정이며,
and then we'll see each other tonight dressed in our best clothes.
그럼 오늘 밤에 다시 만나요 우리가 가장 좋은 옷을 입었습니다.
- OK. - See you.
- 좋아요. - 또 봐요.
- See you tonight. - Thank you.
- 오늘 밤에 만나요. - 감사합니다.
Let them rest.
휴식을 취하게 해주세요.
Jun Kyung, how are you?
준경 씨, 잘 지내요?
Good.
좋은.
How are you, dad?
잘 지내세요, 아빠?
It's nice here.
여기가 좋아요.
Good weather, breeze, sea.
좋은 날씨, 바람, 바다.
And you?
당신은요?
Now I'm at home with Jun Seo.
지금은 서준이랑 집에 있어요.
Yes?
예?
That's very good.
아주 좋은데요.
So, are you going to have dinner together?
그럼 저녁 같이 드실래요?
Wait, dad...
잠깐만요, 아빠...
Yes?
예?
Wait a second.
잠깐만요.
- Dad? - Hello, Jun Seo.
- 아빠? - 안녕, 서준아.
I felt bad for leaving without seeing you,
만나지 않고 떠나서 마음이 아쉬웠어요
but hearing your voice like that makes me feel better.
그런데 그런 목소리를 들으니 기분이 좋아지네요.
- Dad. - Yes?
- 아빠. - 네?
I'm sorry for what happened earlier.
이전에 일어난 일에 대해 사과드립니다.
Have a good time.
즐거운 시간 보내세요.
We don't want to ruin your day, do we?
우리는 당신의 하루를 망치고 싶지 않아요, 그렇죠?
- Come on? - Yes.
- 어서 해봐요? - 예.
They call just to see how I am, even when nothing happens.
그들은 단지 내가 어떤지 보려고 전화를 했고, 아무 일도 일어나지 않더라도.
It is usually the parents those who worry like this.
대개는 부모다. 이렇게 고민하는 분들.
Now that they've grown up, They are the ones who care about me.
이제 그들은 성장했고, 그들은 나를 걱정하는 사람들입니다.
Looks like your kids turned out okay.
당신의 아이들은 괜찮은 것 같습니다.
Yeah.
응.
My daughter is an obstetrician and gynecologist,
내 딸은 산부인과 의사이고,
and my son is doing graduate school.
그리고 내 아들은 대학원에 다니고 있어요.
They are very friendly.
그들은 매우 친절합니다.
You must be proud.
당신은 자랑스러워해야합니다.
But it's not that simple.
그러나 그렇게 간단하지는 않습니다.
My son has not yet found what you love to do,
우리 아들은 아직 못 찾았어요 당신이 좋아하는 일,
and that worries me.
그게 걱정이에요.
My daughter still hasn't found someone to love,
내 딸은 아직 사랑할 사람을 찾지 못했지만,
and that worries me too.
그건 나도 걱정이 된다.
When did we take that photo?
우리가 언제 그 사진을 찍었나요?
Was it the year you started college?
대학에 입학한 해였나요?
It was my orientation day.
저의 오리엔테이션 날이었습니다.
A few months before mom's accident.
엄마의 사고가 있기 몇 달 전.
We look very uncomfortable.
우리는 매우 불편해 보입니다.
Why were we smiling like that?
우리는 왜 그렇게 웃고 있었나요?
You look...
당신은 ...
very good.
매우 좋은.
Dear?
에게?
Know? In retrospect,
알다? 돌이켜 보면,
Our family was not so happy, Even before mom's accident,
우리 가족은 별로 행복하지 않았는데, 엄마가 사고를 당하기 전부터
but we weren't unhappy either.
하지만 우리도 불행하지 않았어요.
Do you think so?
그렇게 생각하시나요?
Of course.
물론.
We were normal.
우리는 정상이었습니다.
We...
우리는...
No, I...
아니, 난...
I think I blamed mom for my unhappiness.
내 불행을 엄마 탓으로 돌린 것 같아요.
It was my fault.
그것은 내 잘못이었습니다.
Gosh, the power went out again.
맙소사, 또 전원이 나갔네요.
- Hey. - Yeah?
- 여기요. - 응?
Do you think this has happened when mom was alone?
이런 일이 일어났다고 생각하시나요? 엄마가 혼자였을 때?
He must have been scared.
무서웠나 봐요.
Yes.
예.
She probably felt lonely too.
아마도 외로움을 느꼈을 것입니다.
Honey,
여보,
why are you in the dark?
당신은 왜 어둠 속에 있나요?
I understand, the power went out.
이해합니다. 전원이 나갔습니다.
Ready.
준비되었습니다.
Now there is light.
이제 빛이 있습니다.
Next time the power goes out, go there...
다음에 정전되면 거기로 가세요...
Honey.
여보.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I shouldn't have said that, I'm sorry.
그런 말을 하지 말았어야 했는데, 미안해요.
Don't cry.
울지 마세요.
You were afraid, right?
두려웠죠?
I'm very sorry.
정말 죄송합니다.
I'm sorry I came home late.
집에 늦게 와서 미안해요.
Honey, don't cry.
여보, 울지 마세요.
It wasn't late.
늦지 않았습니다.
I always had you
나는 항상 당신을 가지고 있었다
at my side
내 옆에
That's why I felt sorry
그래서 미안한 마음이 들었어
and gratitude every day.
그리고 매일 감사합니다.
- Dear. - Don't cry,
- 에게. - 울지 마세요.
everyone is waiting for you outside.
모두가 밖에서 당신을 기다리고 있습니다.
you look
당신은 보인다
amazing today.
오늘 정말 놀랍다.
That?
저것?
That woman, Ja Yeong,
그 여자 자영이요.
It's pretty.
예쁘네요.
It looks good on you.
잘 어울리네요.
Don't say that.
그렇게 말하지 마세요.
Don't hesitate anymore, don't hold back.
더 이상 주저하지 말고, 주저하지 마세요.
you should think
당신은 생각해야
in you
당신 안에
and live for you.
그리고 당신을 위해 살아요.
I want you to be truly happy.
나는 당신이 정말로 행복하기를 바랍니다.
OK.
좋아요.
Every day,
매일,
be happy.
행복하세요.
Dear.
에게.
Dear!
에게!
- Sorry. - Yeah?
- 죄송합니다. - 응?
Is there a tall and thin man middle-aged inside?
키가 크고 마른 남자가 있나요? 내부는 중년?
There is no one.
아무도 없습니다.
Mr. Seo Jin Ho?
서진호 선생님?
Mr. Seo?
서 선생님?
What are you doing here?
여기서 뭐하는거야?
Did something happen?
무슨 일이 있었나요?
Maybe you don't understand
어쩌면 당신은 이해하지 못할 수도 있습니다
why am I like this?
내가 왜 이럴까?
I feel like I'm the only one who lives well...
나만 잘사는거같아...
and that makes me feel very guilty.
그래서 나는 매우 죄책감을 느끼게 됩니다.
It hurts a lot.
많이 아프다.
It would be stranger if you didn't feel that way.
그런 느낌이 없다면 이상한 일이겠죠.
No.
아니요.
You already got over it.
당신은 이미 그것을 극복했습니다.
Someone weak like me,
나처럼 약한 사람은
these feelings...
이 감정들...
You wouldn't understand.
당신은 이해하지 못할 것입니다.
I understand you...
나는 당신을 이해합니다 ...
more than anyone.
누구보다.
My husband was always busy and distant.
남편은 늘 바쁘고 거리를 두었습니다.
When I felt sorry,
미안했을 때
he promised me that,
그는 나에게 그렇게 약속했습니다
when he retired,
그가 은퇴했을 때
we would travel together the pilgrimage path.
우리는 함께 여행할 거예요 순례길.
But he
하지만 그는
he could never keep that promise.
그는 그 약속을 결코 지킬 수 없었습니다.
I thought about it for a long time.
오랜 시간 고민했어요.
"What would it mean to go alone?"
"혼자 간다는 게 무슨 뜻인가요?"
But in the end,
그러나 결국
I went alone,
혼자 갔었어요
like you.
당신을 좋아합니다
Do you know what I packed when I left?
내가 떠날 때 무엇을 챙겼는지 아시나요?
For the last day of the pilgrimage,
순례 마지막 날
for that day...
그날...
I went from hospital to hospital,
병원에서 병원으로 다녔습니다.
gathering sleeping pills.
수면제를 모으는 중
I emptied the jar,
병을 비웠어요
I lay down and lay motionless in bed.
침대에 누웠다가 움직이지 않고 누워있습니다.
And, suddenly,
그리고 갑자기
I felt very sorry for myself.
내 자신이 매우 안타깝습니다.
It wasn't that I wanted to live for my husband.
남편을 위해 살고 싶었던 건 아니었어요.
I felt very pathetic...
정말 한심했습니다...
and my life was unbearably sad.
내 삶은 참을 수 없을 정도로 슬펐습니다.
The life I still had left...
나에게 남은 인생은...
I was too valuable to give up.
포기하기엔 나는 너무 소중한 존재였다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
It must have been difficult to talk about.
이야기하기 어려웠을 것 같아요.
I just wanted to say
그냥 말하고 싶었어
that your life is not over yet.
당신의 인생은 아직 끝나지 않았다는 것을.
They say life is a festival.
인생은 축제라고 하잖아요.
Our festival is not over yet.
우리의 축제는 아직 끝나지 않았습니다.
Do you want to go out?
나가고 싶니?
For our latest song, we are accepting requests.
최신곡 신청을 받고 있습니다.
If you have one...
하나 있다면...
How about a song What would your wife love?
노래는 어때요? 아내는 무엇을 좋아할까요?
No.
아니요.
Let's ask for a song that you like.
좋아하는 노래를 물어보자.
My name is Ja Yeong.
제 이름은 자영이에요.
Jin Ja Yeong.
진자영.
Very good, Ja Yeong.
아주 좋아, 자영아.
Let's listen together to a song that you like.
좋아하는 노래를 함께 들어보자.
Aren't we exaggerating?
과장하는 것 아닌가요?
Come here to look for him?
그를 찾으러 여기로 오세요?
We are not usually this type of family.
우리는 보통 이런 가족이 아닙니다.
Dad must have felt very alone traveling without company.
아빠는 분명 외로움을 느꼈을 거예요 일행 없이 여행하기.
Yes,
네,
It is probable.
그럴 가능성이 높습니다.
By the way,
그건 그렇고,
since when do you say the right thing?
언제부터 옳은 말을 했어?
Yes, well,
네, 글쎄요
I guess your conscience is affecting you.
내 생각엔 당신의 양심이 당신에게 영향을 미치는 것 같아요.
You were busy dating the guy next door, right?
바쁘셨어요 옆집 남자랑 데이트하는 거 맞지?
How long has it been?
얼마나 됐나요?
That?
저것?
I was waiting for an answer. Why so quiet?
나는 대답을 기다리고 있었다. 왜 그렇게 조용합니까?
The truth
진실
It's just that we don't treat each other well as a family.
단지 우리가 서로를 가족처럼 잘 대하지 않는다는 것뿐입니다.
Let's try it.
시도해 봅시다.
Silently, so that no one notices.
아무도 눈치 채지 못하도록 조용히.
Look, there's dad.
보세요, 아빠가 있어요.
Don't make a funny face, do it for him.
웃긴 표정 짓지 말고 그 사람을 위해 그렇게 하세요.
Worry about yourself.
자신에 대해 걱정하십시오.
Everyone in our group They had strong personalities.
우리 그룹의 모든 사람들 그들은 개성이 강했습니다.
Thanks to you,
당신 덕분에,
I had a great time.
나는 즐거운 시간을 보냈습니다.
Me too.
저도요.
This journey will accompany me for a long time.
이 여행은 오랫동안 나와 함께 할 것이다.
- Dad! - Over here!
- 아빠! - 여기요!
It looks good, doesn't it?
좋아 보이는데, 그렇지 않나요?
He's probably holding on.
그는 아마 버티고 있을 거예요.
Say hello well.
인사를 잘 하세요.
Mr. Seo,
서 선생님,
It's time to wake up from oblivion.
이제 망각에서 깨어날 시간입니다.
[Information document about burial in trees]
[정보 문서 수목매장에 대해서]
They say that even the urn will decompose there.
거기에서는 항아리도 썩는다고 하더라고요.
Everything returns to earth.
모든 것은 땅으로 돌아갑니다.
Isn't that a little strange?
좀 이상하지 않나요?
What do you think, dad?
어떻게 생각하세요, 아빠?
You haven't eaten yet, have you?
아직 식사 안 하셨나요?
Is something wrong?
뭔가 문제가 있나요?
No.
아니요.
I know it may sound strange, but...
이상하게 들릴 수도 있다는 건 알지만...
mom passed away,
엄마가 돌아가셨어요,
and you ask if something happens?
그리고 무슨 일이 일어났는지 물어보나요?
Isn't that a little strange?
좀 이상하지 않나요?
How about
어때?
something spicy?
뭔가 매운?
Like what?
어떤가요?
Whatever they want.
그들이 원하는 것은 무엇이든.
So,
그래서,
How about tteokbokki?
떡볶이는 어때요?
Isn't it very spicy?
엄청 맵지 않아요?
You ask for it.
당신은 그것을 요구합니다.
I don't have my phone now. Can you order?
지금은 휴대폰이 없어요. 주문할 수 있나요?
[Julia, Kim Mi Ran]
[줄리아, 김미란]
Well done, Jun Kyung.
수고했어, 준경아.
your mom
네 엄마
I was stuck at home all the time.
나는 항상 집에 갇혀있었습니다.
This open place suits you better.
이 열린 공간이 당신에게 더 잘 어울립니다.
My sister has a tree now.
내 여동생은 지금 나무를 갖고 있어요.
My dear, I may not come often,
자기야, 자주 올 수는 없겠지만
but I will visit you when I can.
하지만 가능할 때 당신을 방문하겠습니다.
Take care of yourself.
몸 조심하세요.
- That's better. - Yes.
- 그게 더 낫네요. - 예.
- It's cute.
- 귀엽네요.
I feel really bad for his dad.
나는 그의 아버지에게 정말 안타까움을 느낀다.
I couldn't live without her.
나는 그녀 없이는 살 수 없었습니다.
What if he does something reckless?
그 사람이 무모한 짓을 하면 어쩌지?
Not only the dead deserve compassion.
죽은 사람만이 동정심을 받을 자격이 있는 것은 아닙니다.
The living too.
생활도요.
Take good care of your dad.
아버지를 잘 돌봐주세요.
Take care of yourself
자신을 돌봐
and stop getting drunk for no reason.
그리고 아무 이유 없이 술에 취하지 마세요.
- Come on. -Have a drink with Jin Ho too.
- 어서 해봐요. - 진호랑도 한잔.
I will do that.
나는 그렇게 할 것이다.
Don't forget the party tonight at six.
오늘 밤 6시에 열리는 파티를 잊지 마세요.
Hello.
안녕하세요.
"Popularize Korean legends with AI"?
"한국 전설을 AI로 대중화한다"?
It sounds boring.
지루한 것 같아요.
Do you want to hear something funny?
재미있는 얘기를 듣고 싶나요?
You know Yuna, right?
윤아 아시죠?
I'll do the choreography for your new song.
신곡 안무는 제가 할게요.
Oh really?
오, 진짜?
What if I become too famous?
내가 너무 유명해지면 어쩌지?
Yes.
예.
- You're annoying. - What are you doing?
- 짜증나잖아. - 뭐하세요?
TRUE.
진실.
Whose choreography was it?
누구의 안무였나요?
It suits you perfectly.
그것은 당신에게 완벽하게 어울립니다.
Yeah? Seem to you?
응? 당신에게 보인다?
It's a bit flashy.
좀 화려하네요.
You are my boyfriend. How would it not work?
당신은 내 남자 친구입니다. 어떻게 작동하지 않습니까?
It's a lot of pressure.
정말 압박감이 크네요.
I'm about to be even more famous,
앞으로 더 유명해질 것 같아요
You better prepare for that.
당신은 그것을 준비하는 것이 좋습니다.
Aren't you sick of plaid shirts?
체크무늬 셔츠가 질리지 않나요?
Hey, isn't that Yoon Sol?
야 윤솔 아니냐?
I think so.
그렇게 생각해요.
It just can't be.
그럴 수 없습니다.
It's me, come.
나야, 와.
I follow you on Instagram,
인스타그램에서 당신을 팔로우하고 있어요.
but you didn't follow me.
하지만 당신은 나를 따르지 않았습니다.
I will do it if you send me a message.
메시지 보내주시면 해드리겠습니다.
Can we take a photo with you?
우리 같이 사진 좀 찍어도 될까요?
- Clear. - Thank you.
- 분명한. - 감사합니다.
- It's very good. - Delicious.
- 아주 좋아요. - 맛있는.
It's tasty, right?
맛있지, 그렇지?
Hey,
안녕,
stop roasting and eat a little.
그만 굽고 좀 먹어라.
I'm eating.
나는 먹고있다.
You look better than you did a few days ago.
며칠 전보다 더 좋아 보여요.
Yes, you must be eating well.
응, 잘 먹고 있겠지.
Eating well?
잘 먹나요?
No, it's because he doesn't have an annoying wife.
아니, 짜증나는 아내가 없기 때문이다.
There you are.
거기 있습니다.
- Our guide arrived. - Hello!
- 우리 가이드가 도착했어요. - 안녕하세요!
How good to see you.
만나서 정말 반가워요.
You're late, right?
늦었지, 그렇지?
I'm late on purpose when I'm free.
나는 한가할 때 일부러 늦는다.
I'm tired of arriving early and take care of everything.
일찍 도착해서 피곤해요 그리고 모든 일을 처리하세요.
It seems like an eternity passed.
영원이 지나간 것 같습니다.
How good to see you all.
모두 만나서 정말 반가워요.
Very well, eat.
좋아요, 먹어요.
- Let's toast. - Clear.
- 건배하자. - 분명한.
Health!
건강!
The marriage you lose will pay for the game, okay?
당신이 잃어버린 결혼 생활 게임 비용을 지불할 거에요, 알았죠?
- Sounds good. - Wait,
- 좋은 것 같아요. - 잠깐만요
They're not even married.
그들은 결혼도 하지 않았습니다.
So what are they?
그럼 그들은 무엇입니까?
- Losing team pays! - Deal done.
- 패한 팀이 비용을 지불합니다! - 거래가 완료되었습니다.
I haven't played in 20 years.
나는 20년 동안 플레이를 하지 않았습니다.
Me neither. It's been more than ten years for me.
나도 마찬가지다. 나에게는 10년 이상이 흘렀다.
Wow,
와,
It looks like we'll pay for everything.
우리가 모든 비용을 지불할 것 같습니다.
Let's do the best we can.
최선을 다하자.
- Everything went well, right? - Yes.
- 모든 일이 잘 진행됐죠? - 예.
Here it comes.
여기 온다.
Thank you, doctor.
고마워요, 박사님.
Both mother and baby are healthy.
산모와 아기 모두 건강합니다.
- Thank you. - Thank you so much.
- 감사합니다. - 매우 감사합니다.
- We appreciate it very much.
- 정말 감사드립니다.
Why did you do that?
왜 그랬어요?
- You should have told him before. - I was going to do it,
- 미리 말했어야지. - 내가 하려고 했는데,
but you know.
하지만 당신은 알고 있습니다.
I
나는
and Jun Kyung...
와 준경이...
We only met a couple of times.
우리는 단지 몇 번 만났습니다.
In the store...
가게에서 ...
when I gave him a ride...
내가 그 사람을 태워줬을 때...
If I had told him: "I have a son..."
내가 그에게 "나에게는 아들이 있어요..."라고 말했다면...
I couldn't do that.
나는 그렇게 할 수 없었다.
And then we started dating...
그리고 우리는 데이트를 시작했습니다 ...
and I didn't know
그리고 난 몰랐어
When to tell the truth.
진실을 말해야 할 때.
I know it all seems like an excuse, but...
다 핑계인거 알지만...
Yes, I understand.
네, 이해합니다.
When he said we should go slow,
천천히 가자고 했을 때,
I thought, "Okay,
나는 "그래,
I will wait for the right moment."
적절한 순간을 기다리겠다"고 말했다.
That's what I repeated to myself.
그것이 내가 나 자신에게 반복한 것입니다.
Hey,
안녕,
you liked him a lot.
당신은 그를 많이 좋아했습니다.
So,
그래서,
Why don't you contact her again?
그 사람한테 다시 연락해 보는 게 어때?
We're done.
이제 끝났습니다.
Tell me.
말해 보세요.
Let's hear your excuse.
변명을 들어보자.
At that moment,
그 순간
I realized.
나는 깨달았다.
I like it a lot more than I thought.
생각보다 너무 마음에 듭니다.
I am very sure of that.
나는 그것을 확신합니다.
That's why I need to see it again.
그래서 다시 봐야겠어요.
When I was 20,
내가 20살이었을 때,
It was very...
그것은 매우...
immature
미성숙한
Well...
음...
I still am a little.
나는 아직 조금이다.
My ex-girlfriend called me...
전여친이 전화했는데..
Two months after we broke up.
헤어진 지 두 달.
She said she was pregnant.
그녀는 임신했다고 말했습니다.
Suddenly...
갑자기...
the idea of having a child...
아이를 갖는다는 생각..
honestly...
솔직히...
It scared me.
겁이 났어요.
As for
에 관해서는
I saw his face...
그 사람 얼굴을 봤는데...
I felt overwhelmed...
압도당하는 기분이었는데...
and moved.
그리고 움직였다.
I was...
나는 ...
strangely moved.
이상하게 움직였다.
That's how I felt.
나는 그렇게 느꼈다.
but
하지만
we were already done,
우리는 이미 끝났어요
and try to return
그리고 돌아오려고 노력해
just for responsibility...
단지 책임감 때문에...
It wasn't possible.
그것은 불가능했습니다.
My ex took the baby and went to Germany to study.
내 전 애인이 아기를 데려갔어 그리고 독일로 유학을 갔다.
We contacted again
우리 또 연락했는데
last year.
작년에.
my son
내 아들
He wanted to meet me.
그는 나를 만나고 싶어했습니다.
I wanted to live in Korea.
저는 한국에서 살고 싶었어요.
So...
그래서...
after 14 years,
14년 후,
I met him.
나는 그를 만났다.
What's it called?
이름이 뭐예요?
Daniel.
다니엘.
Im Daniel.
나는 다니엘이다.
He is 15
그는 15세이다
and it is very tall.
그리고 키가 아주 커요.
He's in that cynical teenage phase, right?
그 사람은 냉소적인 10대 시절이죠, 그렇죠?
Yes,
네,
Exactly.
정확합니다.
That little boy...
그 꼬마...
while growing up...
자라면서...
I couldn't do anything for him.
나는 그를 위해 아무것도 할 수 없었습니다.
That is.
즉.
That's my excuse.
그게 내 변명이에요.
What I really wanted to tell you...
내가 꼭 말해주고 싶었던 건...
no excuses...
변명의 여지가 없습니다 ...
is that...
그게...?
I'm very sorry.
정말 죄송합니다.
I've already forgiven you.
나는 이미 당신을 용서했습니다.
From the moment I saw your face a while ago
네 얼굴을 본 순간부터 얼마 전
I have something I want to give you.
당신에게 주고 싶은 것이 있습니다.
Wait, you had this?
잠깐, 이거 가지고 있었어?
If we hadn't finished,
우리가 끝나지 않았다면,
you would still listen to music one-sided forever.
넌 아직도 음악을 듣겠지 영원히 일방적이다.
Thanks to you, We didn't have to pay for the game,
당신 덕분에, 우리는 게임 비용을 지불할 필요가 없었습니다.
But I feel bad for the others.
하지만 다른 사람들에게는 기분이 좋지 않습니다.
You don't seem that sorry. You tried so hard.
별로 미안해 보이지는 않네요. 당신은 정말 열심히 노력했습니다.
I'm not usually competitive.
나는 보통 경쟁적이지 않습니다.
but tonight I didn't want to lose.
하지만 오늘 밤 나는지고 싶지 않았습니다.
Oh really? Because?
오, 진짜? 왜냐하면?
I don't mind losing alone, but you would have lost too.
혼자 지는 건 상관없어 하지만 너도 졌을 거야.
- You're very kind. - No, come on.
- 정말 친절하시네요. - 아니, 어서.
I'm serious.
나는 진지하다.
You are tall for your age,
나이에 비해 키가 크군요.
You don't have a belly or anything.
당신은 배도 없고 아무것도 없습니다.
I'm holding her back right now.
나는 지금 그녀를 붙잡고 있습니다.
If you dyed your gray hair a little...
흰머리 좀 염색했으면..
Maybe you would look younger than me.
어쩌면 당신은 나보다 젊어 보일 수도 있습니다.
You said it was ten years ago that you didn't play bowling.
10년 전 일이라고 했잖아 볼링을 안 쳤다고.
How come you played so well?
어떻게 그렇게 잘 놀았나요?
I try hard not to forget, that's all.
나는 잊지 않으려고 노력한다. 그게 다다.
When things are difficult, I try to forget,
상황이 어려울 때, 잊으려고 노력하고,
and when things are good,
그리고 상황이 좋을 때,
I try not to do it.
나는 그것을하지 않으려 고 노력합니다.
Does that work when you want it to?
당신이 원할 때 그게 효과가 있나요?
Are you curious?
궁금하신가요?
Is this okay?
괜찮나요?
What thing?
무슨 일?
Let him come like this to see a woman who lives alone.
혼자 사는 여자를 만나러 이렇게 오게 해주세요.
you will not have
당신은 없을 것입니다
Weird ideas, right?
이상한 아이디어죠?
That?
저것?
No, don't get me wrong.
아니요, 오해하지 마세요.
I got scared.
나는 겁이났다.
This is Bom.
봄이에요.
Hello.
안녕하세요.
- I didn't scare her, did I? - Not at all.
- 난 그 사람을 겁주지 않았죠? - 별말씀을요.
Did you have fun today? Greet him.
오늘은 즐거웠나요? 그에게 인사하세요.
This place used to be a pool hall.
이곳은 원래 당구장이었습니다.
With my work and my personality, I move a lot.
나의 일과 성격으로 인해 나는 많이 움직인다.
I never needed a place that felt like my home.
난 절대 장소가 필요하지 않았어 그곳이 내 집 같았어요.
A little unusual, isn't it?
조금 특이하지 않나요?
No,
아니요,
I think it's wonderful.
나는 그것이 훌륭하다고 생각한다.
It feels
느낌
like a hiding place.
마치 은신처처럼.
You are a person...
당신은 사람입니다 ...
incredible.
믿을 수 없는.
Some buy souvenirs,
기념품을 구매하시는 분들도 계시고,
take photos
사진을 찍다
and publish them on social networks,
소셜 네트워크에 게시하고,
but me
하지만 나
just drawing.
그냥 그리는 중.
I draw the things I want to remember,
기억하고 싶은 것들을 그려요.
the things that I felt,
내가 느낀 것들,
the people I met and the conversations we had,
내가 만난 사람들 그리고 우리가 나눴던 대화들,
so as not to forget them.
그들을 잊지 않도록.
That's how I remember things.
그것이 내가 기억하는 방식이다.
What do you want to remember now?
지금 무엇을 기억하고 싶나요?
Can I see it?
볼 수 있나요?
- Yeah. - Gracias.
- 응. - 그라시아스.
Vaya.
바야.
He still has a lot to go.
그는 아직 갈 길이 멀다.
Are you really Seo Jun Seo?
진짜 서준서 맞나요?
- That? - What's that?
- 저것? - 그게 뭐죠?
Are they punishing you or something?
그들이 당신을 처벌하고 있나요?
- It doesn't suit me, does it? - No not at all.
- 나한테는 안 맞는 것 같죠? - 전혀 그렇지 않아요.
Sol bought it for me.
솔이 나한테 사줬어.
It doesn't suit you.
그것은 당신에게 적합하지 않습니다.
I thought so too.
나도 그렇게 생각했다.
Why do they go out if they don't even match?
일치하지도 않는데 왜 나가나요?
Because I like it.
내가 그것을 좋아하기 때문에.
Because she's pretty, right?
왜냐면 그 사람은 예쁘거든요, 그렇죠?
Well,
글쎄,
It's great.
훌륭해요.
He knows what he wants.
그는 자신이 원하는 것이 무엇인지 알고 있습니다.
It does everything well.
그것은 모든 것을 잘 수행합니다.
Why would you like me,
왜 나를 좋아하겠어요?
a loser?
패자?
Why are you a loser?
당신은 왜 패자입니까?
You're great too.
당신도 훌륭해요.
Oh really?
오, 진짜?
In what sense?
어떤 의미에서?
She's always busy,
그녀는 항상 바쁘다.
It always makes you nervous.
그것은 항상 당신을 긴장하게 만듭니다.
It is very thin, I don't even think she's that pretty,
엄청 얇아요, 난 그 사람이 그렇게 예쁘다고 생각하지도 않는데,
but you are always on his side.
하지만 당신은 항상 그의 편입니다.
Yeah, that's what makes you a cool guy.
그래, 그게 널 멋진 남자로 만드는 거야.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
What does it matter if you think I'm cool?
내가 멋지다고 생각하는 게 무슨 상관이야?
Sol is the one who should think that.
솔은 그렇게 생각해야 한다.
Why can't it be me?
왜 나는 될 수 없습니까?
Let's stop.
그만하자.
See you later.
나중에 봐요.
Dad?
아빠?
A grandmother from my sister's town raised Bom.
봄은 언니 동네 할머니가 키웠어요.
He passed away, and Bom was left alone.
그는 세상을 떠났고, 봄만 홀로 남았다.
That's horrible.
정말 끔찍해요.
I felt alone, so I took her in,
외롭다고 느껴서 그녀를 받아들였어요
but more time passes in the nursery than with me.
하지만 시간이 더 흐르고 나보다 보육원에서.
I tell myself I'm busy,
바쁘다고 스스로에게 말하지만
and I think that makes her feel alone.
내 생각엔 그게 그녀를 외롭다고 느끼게 만드는 것 같아요.
Is the man in the drawing your husband?
그림 속 남자가 당신의 남편인가요?
Never!
절대!
No? What a relief.
아니요? 정말 다행이네요.
It was part of a couples tour
커플 여행의 일부였습니다.
and he wouldn't stop flirting with me.
그리고 그는 나를 유혹하는 것을 멈추지 않을 것입니다.
His wife was there. What was I thinking?
그의 아내가 거기에 있었습니다. 나는 무엇을 생각하고 있었습니까?
It was a cruise ship, so there was no escape.
크루즈선이라 탈출은 불가능했다.
It was very uncomfortable and annoying.
매우 불편하고 짜증났습니다.
I drew him to curse him for life.
평생 욕하고 싶어서 그렸습니다.
That?
저것?
That guy is an idiot.
그 사람은 바보입니다.
Married and disgusting, seriously.
결혼하고 역겹다, 진심으로.
Do you curse too?
너도 욕해?
Anyone with common sense would do it.
상식이 있는 사람이라면 누구나 그렇게 할 것이다.
He's a damn.
그는 빌어 먹을입니다.
- You can answer. - OK.
- 대답하시면 됩니다. - 좋아요.
[My son]
[내 아들]
Hello, Jun Seo.
안녕하세요, 서준님.
That?
저것?
Is it already that late?
벌써 그렇게 늦었나요?
Yes.
예.
I'm just with some friends.
나는 단지 몇몇 친구들과 함께 있을 뿐입니다.
OK. I'll be home soon, don't worry.
좋아요. 곧 집에 갈 테니 걱정하지 마세요.
I'm coming.
나는 간다.
I said I'm on my way.
나는 지금 가는 중이라고 말했다.
Bye bye.
안녕.
You should go home.
집에 가야 해요.
Yes.
예.
There are no more drinks anyway.
어쨌든 더 이상 음료수는 없습니다.
and it's too late.
그리고 너무 늦었어요.
Hey, Boom...
안녕, 붐...
I'm leaving
나는 떠난다
I hope we can see each other again.
우리가 다시 만날 수 있기를 바랍니다.
Take care of yourself.
몸 조심하세요.
Leave.
떠나다.
Do you want to stay the night?
밤새 머물고 싶나요?
Weren't you going home?
집에 가는 거 아니었어?
I felt like I needed another drink,
한잔 더 마시고 싶은 기분이었는데,
so I stopped by the store.
그래서 가게에 들렀어요.
Seriously...
진심으로...
can I stay the night?
밤에 묵을 수 있나요?
- Don't you have a boyfriend? - Yes, but it's not good for Sol.
- 남자친구 없어요? - 예, 하지만 솔에게는 좋지 않습니다.
He's a graduate loser,
그는 대학원생 패배자입니다.
so I would try it.
그래서 시도해 보겠습니다.
- I want to say it's love, but... - Call the police!
- 사랑이라고 말하고 싶지만... - 경찰에 신고하세요!
Do you think I will be in Sol's future?
내가 솔이의 미래에 있을 것 같나요?
I was afraid that people would notice
사람들이 눈치챌까봐 두려웠어요
how much I like you.
내가 당신을 얼마나 좋아하는지
Do you really think that Julia
정말 줄리아가 그렇게 생각하시나요
would I want to see you punish yourself like this?
당신이 이렇게 자신을 처벌하는 모습을 보고 싶나요?
You don't have to blame yourself.
자책할 필요는 없습니다.
I'm tired of worrying for what others think.
걱정에 지쳤어요 다른 사람들이 어떻게 생각하는지.
Dad?
아빠?
What was that?
그게 뭐였나요?
Hello.
안녕하세요.
Daniel, I want you to meet my girlfriend.
다니엘, 내 여자친구를 만나보고 싶어요.
Are you cooking? That's new.
요리 중이신가요? 새로운 내용입니다.
Why are you so nice to him?
당신은 그 사람에게 왜 그렇게 친절합니까?
She's crazy.
그 사람은 미쳤어요.
I'm sorry, Jun Kyung.
미안해요 준경 씨.
What? Have they already left you?
뭐? 그들은 이미 당신을 떠났나요?